"Risks and Benefits of
Nicotinic Acid (NA), a NAD+ Booster"
The name nicotinic acid was
changed to niacin in the 1940s
to avoid any confusion
with nicotine.
Either name has to be better
than the original moniker, though:
vitamin PP
(for pellagra preventing).
In the 1950s, NA became the world’s
first cholesterol-lowering drug.
This led to more than 20 trials involving
tens of thousands of individuals
taking high doses of
NA for up to six years,
resulting in by far the most
robust safety data we have
on any of the NAD+ precursors.
The most striking benefit was found
in the Coronary Drug Project,
a trial carried out in the pre-statin
drug era of the 1960s and 70s.
The 15-year follow-up found that
those who had been randomized
to years of high-dose NA ended up
with a 6.2% drop in absolute mortality
(52% had died in the NA group
versus 58% in the placebo group).
This sparked major clinical trials that,
sadly, failed so spectacularly
that one was even
stopped prematurely.
All in all, a Cochrane meta-
analysis concluded that
“no evidence of benefits from
niacin therapy” was found.
One possible explanation
for the contrasting results
is that the early promising trials
used immediate release niacin,
while the newer failed trials
used slow release formulations
(also known as extended
or sustained release).
At high doses, regular niacin commonly
causes an intense flushing redness
and prickly heat sensation similar
to a menopausal hot flash.
A slow release version was developed
to reduce this flushing reaction,
catapulting it into a billion-
dollar blockbuster drug,
but it simply doesn’t work as
well to lower cholesterol.
The major clinical trial failures led
to the withdrawal of the drug in Europe
and the removal from
U.S. clinical guidelines
for cardiovascular
disease prevention.
There still may be a role
for niacin preparations
in the treatment
of heart disease
among patients who cannot
tolerate statin drugs,
but what about use for the
general public as an NAD+ booster?
There is a series of
rare genetic defects
that can lead to a condition
called mitochondrial myopathy
that’s characterized by low NAD+
levels in the blood and muscles.
In 2020, researchers demonstrated
that these levels could be repleted
with 750 to 1,000 mg
a day of NA,
which led to a significant
improvement in muscle strength.
This was the first and only study to show
improvements in muscle NAD+ levels
and performance with
any sort of NAD+ booster.
In a control group of individuals
without the genetic defect,
blood levels of NAD+
were raised by NA,
but not muscle levels,
suggesting that NAD+ levels are
already “topped off” in normal muscles.
As you’ll see, this is a recurring
theme among NAD+ boosters.
We know that large doses of NA
can boost NAD+ levels in human blood,
but a corresponding increase in sirtuin
activity has yet to be demonstrated.
Why not give it a try?
Because of the side effects unearthed
in the cholesterol-lowering trials.
NA raises blood sugars and may increase
your risk of developing diabetes.
Based on studies of tens of thousands
of people on high-dose NA
who were followed for years,
one would expect that 1 in 43
people taking NA for five years
would develop diabetes who
otherwise wouldn’t have.
It’s unclear if this risk is only limited
to slow release formulations.
The safety buffer, the ratio between
the tolerable upper limit and the RDA,
is the lowest for NA compared to
half a dozen other common vitamins.
However, the upper limit is just
based on the flushing reaction,
which although uncomfortable,
is considered harmless
and tends to dissipate over time.
Long-term use can have other
adverse consequences, though,
including stomach ulcers,
vomiting, abdominal pain,
diarrhea, and jaundice,
a sign of liver toxicity,
which is worse with
slow-release formulations.
There is also a theoretical concern
that excessive NA intake
may contribute to the development
of Parkinson’s disease.
Due to the unpleasant flushing and
risk of more serious side effects,
interest has moved towards
other NAD+ enhancers.